<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Nomadery | johnchapin.boostrot.net]]></title>
  <link href="http://johnchapin.boostrot.net/blog/categories/nomadery/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://johnchapin.boostrot.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-30T22:43:59+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://johnchapin.boostrot.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Chapin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Digital Nomad's Guide to Onward Travel]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnchapin.boostrot.net/blog/2013/12/30/the-digital-nomads-guide-to-onward-travel/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-30T15:30:36+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnchapin.boostrot.net/blog/2013/12/30/the-digital-nomads-guide-to-onward-travel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Like many travelers, I didn&rsquo;t realize that <strong>airlines can and will refuse to board passengers who might be denied entry to their destination.</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://imgur.com/qDNQBmC"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/qDNQBmC.jpg" title="Hosted by imgur.com"/></a></p>

<p>The country you&rsquo;re trying to enter also wants to ensure that you leave. Many countries do this by making sure you have confirmed (and paid) travel arrangements to exit the country. This is called <strong>proof of onward travel.</strong></p>

<!-- more -->


<blockquote><p><strong>Proof of onward travel</strong> generally means <strong>&ldquo;confirmed and paid travel arrangements with a final destination outside of this country.&rdquo;</strong></p>

<p>In some cases, you can add <strong>&ldquo;and without the possibility of the traveler being returned to this country for some reason.&rdquo;</strong></p></blockquote>

<p>If an airline delivers you to a country, and you&rsquo;re denied entry because you don&rsquo;t have proof of onward travel, that airline may be forced to return you to the flight&rsquo;s origin, at their expense.</p>

<p>In some cases, you&rsquo;ll already have valid travel arrangements that you intend to keep, and those will be accepted as proof of onward travel. However, as a digital nomad, I often <strong>don&rsquo;t know which country I&rsquo;m going to next</strong>, so I need a way to <strong>show proof of onward travel without actually committing myself to a destination.</strong></p>

<p>This article explores the theory and methods behind showing proof of onward travel in a flexible, nomad-friendly way.</p>

<h3>Fully-refundable tickets!</h3>

<p>Those very same airlines who require proof of onward travel are also more than happy to sell it to you, in the form of fully-refundable tickets.</p>

<p>Read that again. <strong>Fully. Refundable. Tickets.</strong></p>

<p>You can buy these tickets for any itinerary, get a confirmation and guaranteed seats, and then later get your purchase price refunded in full with no questions asked.</p>

<h3>Always be heading home.</h3>

<p>When I buy fully-redundable tickets to show proof of onward travel, I make sure that the <strong>destination is my home country.</strong> I think this is a very important point that is often overlooked.</p>

<p>Consider this scenario:</p>

<blockquote><p>You&rsquo;re a citizen of the <em>Alphatina</em>.</p>

<p>You arrive in <em>Betastan</em>, and present proof of onward travel to <em>Gammaralia</em>.</p>

<p><strong>The <em>Betastani</em> border control officer denies you entry, because&hellip;</strong></p>

<p>If you leave <em>Betastan</em> and are denied entry to <em>Gammaralia</em> (because you don&rsquo;t have proof of onward travel from there), you could end up back in <em>Betastan</em>. Rather than take a chance, <em>Betastan</em> might simply deny you entry and avoid having to possibly deal with any shenanigans.</p></blockquote>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a better plan:</p>

<blockquote><p>You&rsquo;re a citizen of <em>Alphatina</em>.</p>

<p>You arrive in <em>Betastan</em>, and present your proof of onward travel back to <em>Alphatina</em>.</p>

<p><strong>The <em>Betastani</em> border control officer welcomes you!</strong></p>

<p>While in <em>Betastan</em>, you get a refund for your <em>Alphatina</em> ticket, and purchase a new one-way ticket to <em>Gammaralia</em>, and a new fully-refundable ticket from <em>Gammaralia</em> back to <em>Alphatina</em>.</p>

<p>You arrive in <em>Gammaralia</em>, and present your proof of onward travel back to <em>Alphatina</em>.</p>

<p><strong>The <em>Gammaralese</em> border control officer welcomes you!</strong></p>

<p>Rinse, repeat&hellip;</p></blockquote>

<p>Having <strong>proof of onward travel</strong> to your home country means that you will <strong>never be denied entry, because you&rsquo;ve always got a ticket home.</strong></p>

<h3>Downsides of fully-refundable tickets</h3>

<ul>
<li>They are very, very, expensive ($3,000+ for a <strong>fully-refundable one-way ticket</strong> from SE Asia to LAX).</li>
<li>You must proactively apply for the refund.</li>
<li>Refunds take time to process, and&hellip;</li>
<li>Depending on that timing, you may have to pay your credit card bill before the refund posts. Airlines won&rsquo;t refund credit card interest charges.</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ve had several very good experiences buying and refunding tickets on <a href="http://www.united.com">United</a>. I&rsquo;ve also used Delta, but have had two somewhat hairy refund experiences that had to be completed over the phone.</p>

<p>In one case, I even purchased <strong>fully-refundable tickets</strong> as <strong>proof of onward travel</strong> at the ticket counter, to avoid being denied boarding and missing my flight (see above FB status.)</p>

<h3>Real tickets are real!</h3>

<p>Despite the fact that you&rsquo;re going to refund them later, the tickets you&rsquo;re buying are <strong>real</strong>, and you&rsquo;ll need a valid credit card and the correct passenger information to complete the purchase process. Last but not least, don&rsquo;t forget to either <strong>print off the confirmation page and e-tickets, or save them as PDF files</strong> to your mobile device so you have them handy!</p>

<h3>Exit cards?</h3>

<p>Many countries require you to fill out an exit card (often a tear-off card attached to the landing card). Fill these out with your onward travel information, but <strong>don&rsquo;t worry</strong>, because as long as you aren&rsquo;t overstaying your visa, it only matters that you&rsquo;re leaving.</p>

<h3>But.. but&hellip;</h3>

<p>This article tries to outline the most comprehensive way to deal with the challenge of onward travel. Everyone has their own experiences and anecdotes, and I&rsquo;ve found that most countries and airlines actually don&rsquo;t ask for proof of onward travel. However, when they do, it might be too late to sort it out! There are many other, less-expensive (but less reliable) ways to prove onward travel as well, so don&rsquo;t be afraid to do your own destination-specific research!</p>

<p>If you have questions, feel free to post them in the comments section and I&rsquo;ll do my best to help out!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oases of the Digital Nomad]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnchapin.boostrot.net/blog/2013/03/05/oases-of-the-digital-nomad/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-05T15:30:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnchapin.boostrot.net/blog/2013/03/05/oases-of-the-digital-nomad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The weekday routine in Ciudad de Panama:</p>

<ol>
<li>Wake up, get out of bed, drag a comb across my head.</li>
<li>Eat breakfast.</li>
<li>GTFO before it gets too hot.</li>
<li>Find an oasis.</li>
</ol>


<!-- more -->


<h3>Oasis #1: New York Bagel Café, El Cangrejo</h3>

<p>The good:</p>

<ul>
<li>Consistent wifi, several accessible power outlets.</li>
<li>Tasty, relatively inexpensive food and bottomless coffee.</li>
<li>Easy access via the Via España bus line.</li>
<li>Loads of expats.</li>
</ul>


<p>The bad:</p>

<ul>
<li>Loads of expats.</li>
<li>Generally terrible music, increasing in volume throughout the day.</li>
<li>Impressively unpleasant chairs.</li>
</ul>


<p>We ended up at the NYBC almost every other day. It was so consistent that it almost became hard to take a chance on something else, knowing we could have a good experience at NYBC.</p>

<p><a href="http://imgur.com/QeH3ACq"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/QeH3ACq.jpg" alt="" /></a><br/>
Einstein&rsquo;s head, carefully enlarged, preserved, and mounted outside of the NYBC in El Cangrejo.</p>

<h3>Oasis #2: Bon Vivant, San Francisco</h3>

<p>The good:</p>

<ul>
<li>Reasonable wifi</li>
<li>Uncrowded (except during lunch)</li>
<li>Excellent food, especially the croissants</li>
</ul>


<p>The bad:</p>

<ul>
<li>Hard to get to via bus from Parque Lefevre. We ended up walking 3+ miles roundtrip.</li>
<li>Packed during lunch. Great for business, but not conducive to tele-working.</li>
<li>Relatively expensive food, few vegetarian options.</li>
</ul>


<p>Bon Vivant was recommended via a response to my inquiry on the &ldquo;Americans in Panama&rdquo; Yahoo group. We ended up going there twice &ndash; might have been back more often, but it was a bit of a hike to get to from our house in Parque Lefevre. Cutting through Parque Omar Torrijos got us away from the traffic and trash (and uncovered manholes), but a 3+ mile roundtrip in CdP is a lot, especially if you don&rsquo;t want to be a puddle of sweat at your destination.</p>

<h3>Oasis #3: Churreria Manolo, El Cangrejo and Obarrio</h3>

<p>The good:</p>

<ul>
<li>Good wifi</li>
<li>Extensive menu</li>
<li>Uncrowded</li>
</ul>


<p>The bad:</p>

<ul>
<li>No power outlets (in the El Cangrejo location)</li>
<li>Mediocre food</li>
<li>Grumpy waitstaff (even for Panama!)</li>
</ul>


<p>Another recommendation, this time from <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/Panama/comments/176xy4/recommend_a_good_coffee_shop_w_wifi_in_panama_city/">/r/panama</a>. We went to the Obarrio location in the evening, after a day of walking around and trying to find wifi in one of the big malls downtown. It&rsquo;s tucked off of Calle 50, and was extremely quiet. IIRC, we were one of only a few patrons, and definitely the only ones with laptops out.</p>

<p>The El Cangrejo location had a better overall vibe, with more customers and a livelier setting in general, although we probably wouldn&rsquo;t have gone had NYBC not been closed for Carnavales. Which might explain why the waitstaff were a little grumpy &ndash; they had to work instead of partying!</p>

<h3>Never worked in:</h3>

<p><strong>Petit Paris</strong> in Marbella. Delicious food&hellip;</p>

<p>PSA: Google Maps is just dead wrong about the location of this place. It&rsquo;s just north of Cinta Costera, in the Marbella neighborhood. The map on their website is accurate.</p>

<h3>Never made it to:</h3>

<p><strong>Café Sucre</strong> and <strong>Bajareque</strong> in Casco Viejo.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Out Into the World.]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnchapin.boostrot.net/blog/2013/01/17/out-into-the-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-17T16:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnchapin.boostrot.net/blog/2013/01/17/out-into-the-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Several people have asked me, &ldquo;John, you handsome devil, how exactly did you manage to arrange your life to be able to pick up and go out into the world with no plans and no return ticket?&rdquo;</p>

<p>The answer, for me at least, was and is &ldquo;persistence&rdquo;. I have persistently and obsessively, over the course of several months, poured over the details of my life and made sure that every action I took moved me closer to location independence. Not all of those decisions have been easy or straightforward.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="http://imgur.com/Nm61Nev"><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Nm61Nevl.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>In no particular order, here&rsquo;s what I had to do.</p>

<h3>Set the date and first location.</h3>

<p>A wonderful friend made this very easy. Gerald and his lovely fiance Piali (now lovely wife!) decided to have a destination wedding at Playa Bonita resort, just west of Panama City, Panama. With plane tickets purchased and a resort booked, we were definitely getting on a plane to Panama in mid-January.</p>

<p>Having a date on the calendar made it a lot easier to work backwards and start sorting out everything else.</p>

<h3>Give up my beloved dog, Maggie.</h3>

<p>She was my rock during a rough patch in my life, and saying goodbye wasn&rsquo;t easy. Fortunately, my good friend Chris was interested in taking her. A three-day, cross-country road trip ensued, and now she&rsquo;s living it up in Boise, Idaho.</p>

<p>With a cool climate, an awesome owner, and some new canine friends, Maggie is a very happy dog :&ndash;)</p>

<h3>Find tenants for my house.</h3>

<p>Looking for tenants is never fun. Looking for tenants in a college town in the middle of November seemed like a terrible idea. Fortune smiled again, as I quickly found two sets of tenants to rent my house over the next 18 months, with no gaps in occupancy and at reasonable rents.</p>

<h3>Get rid of almost everything.</h3>

<p>What a pain. After countless trips to Goodwill, the Salvation Army, and the local dump, I ended up with &frac12; a shed of mostly tools, some kitchen equipment, a few mementos, and lots of specialty running and biking gear. That still seems like &frac12; a shed too much, but I ran out of time before I ran out of inventory!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m jealous of Jeca, who managed to get everything she didn&rsquo;t bring to Panama into 4 bins!</p>

<h3>Sell my car.</h3>

<p>I needed the car until almost the last minute, so I didn&rsquo;t post a for sale ad until about 3 weeks before we left the country. With time running out, I advertised a good price, and accepted an offer for a quick sale with a week to go.</p>

<h3>Adjust my employment situation.</h3>

<p>This kept me up at night. I was very happy and gainfully employed, but also ready to leave a job that I loved so that I could travel. I had a very vague backup plan in place (consulting, or something).</p>

<p>However, my current employer (<a href="http://www.roomkey.com">Roomkey</a>) was extremely supportive of my plans, and agreed to let me work 100% remotely. I&rsquo;m looking forward to writing more about this arrangement, and its positives and negatives as it becomes a part of my day-to-day life.</p>

<h3>Hoodwink the man.</h3>

<p>Despite no longer being physically present in the US, I need to receive tax documents, rent checks, and a few other odd and ends via the USPS. I set up an account with a mail forwarding service that will allow me to receive physical mail at a US address. Through a web interface, I can direct that mail to be shredded, scanned, or forwarded. They&rsquo;ll even forward checks to my bank!</p>

<p>The downside is that the difference between a mailing address and a physical address still eludes some people and institutions (like my city government in Virginia). This topic deserves its own article, so stay tuned for more.</p>

<p>So&hellip;</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it in a nutshell. This kind of lifestyle change is possible for almost anyone, given sufficient motivation.</p>

<p>If you want to do it, do it.</p>

<p>And, if you&rsquo;re read this far, go check out my girlfriend and traveling companion&rsquo;s far more interesting blog here: <a href="http://jecaarmstrong.blogspot.com/">Calle 90</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
